Richard Feynman was one of the most extraordinary scientists
理查德·费曼是20世纪
of the 20th century.
最杰出的科学家之一
As a brilliant physicist,
作为一个聪明的物理学家
he pioneered an entirely new area of his subject.
他在物理学方面开创了一个全新的领域
He's discovered a new law of nature, only a very few people did that.
他发现了一条新的自然规律，只有极少数人知道
The most numerically precise physical theory ever invented.
这是有史以来数值上最精确的物理理论
Yet, he scorned the Nobel Prize he received for this work.
但是，他却轻视通过自己的努力获得的诺贝尔奖
I've already got the prize.
我已经得到了奖品
The prize is the pleasure of finding the thing out.
奖品就是发现这件事物的喜悦
The kick in the discovery.
发现的时候就是中奖的时候
Feynman's brilliance helped shape history.
费曼的才华帮着重塑了历史
As a young man, he helped to build the atom bomb,
在年轻的时候，他参与建造了原子弹
ending the Second World War.
结束了第二次世界大战
And yet, throughout his life, Feynman rejected authority
可是，纵观他的一生，费曼拒绝权威
and refused to conform,
拒绝顺从
preferring instead to follow his passions -
宁可取而代之地顺从自己的热情--
from bongo playing to biology,
从玩邦哥鼓到生物学
from poetry to painting,
从写诗到绘画
from computing to cracking safes.
从计算机到开保险箱
Feynman's fascination with the world knew no bounds.
费曼的魅力广为人知
And in his dying days,
在他去世前的日子里
as a maverick investigator on the Challenger shuttle disaster,
作为一个持不同观点的调查员
调查挑战者号航天飞机遇难事故
he confronted the Washington establishment
他面对华盛顿机构
to reveal the truth about what went wrong.
去揭露真相，到底是什么原因导致的事故
This stuff that I got out of your seal,
这是一块我取自密封舱的垫圈
and I put it in ice water.
然后我把它放进冰水里
Above all, Feynman's infectious enthusiasm for life
特别是，费曼对待生活具有感染力的热情
captivated millions of readers and viewers.
吸引了成千上万的读者和观众
Feynman's been a showman pretty much his whole life.
费曼成了一个表演者，几乎一生都在表演
Any room he walked into, everyone is looking at him.
他走进任何一个房间，所有人的目光都会聚集到他身上
He was the centre of attention.
他是被关注的焦点
Electrons behave exactly the same in this respect as protons.
电子的行为在这一方面和质子是一样的
That is, they're both screwy, but in exactly the same way.
也就是说，它们都是扭曲的，但却是用同一个方式
Here, in his own words and those of the people who knew him best,
本片通过他自己的话，和最了解他的人
this is the story of the most captivating communicator
讲述一个在科学史上最有魅力的
in the history of science.
传播者的故事
But you got to stop and think about the complexity,
但是你得停下来，去思考事物的复杂性
the INCONCEIVABLE nature of nature!
不可思议的大自然的本质
神奇的费曼先生
我生于无知，而且只有很少的时间来
改变各种无知的状况
理查德•费曼
When my mother was pregnant first,
当我母亲怀了第一胎的时候
my father said, "If he's a boy,
我的父亲就说，“如果是个男孩”
"I want him to be a scientist."
“我想让他成为一个科学家”
Richard Phillips Feynman was born on the 11th May 1918,
理查德·菲利普·费曼1918年9月11日出生
during the Depression,
在大萧条时期
to working-class parents living in the outskirts of New York.
工薪阶层的父母住在纽约的市郊
Even when I was a small boy,
即使当我还是个孩子的时候
Poppa used to sit me on his lap
爸爸过去经常让我坐在他的膝盖上
and read to me from the Encyclopaedia Britannica.
念不列颠百科全书给我听
And he would read, say, about dinosaurs.
他也会读，说，关于恐龙的故事
It would say something like,
他会这样说比如
"This thing is 25 feet high
“这个东西有25英尺高”
"and the head is six feet across."
“它的头有6英尺宽”
And so, he'd stop always and say, "Let's see what that means.
所以，他总是停下来说，“让我们看看那意味着什么”
"That would mean that if he stood in our front yard,
“那就意味着如果它站在我们家的前院”
"he would be high enough to put his head through the window.
“它就高的足以把它的头伸进窗户里来”
"But not quite, cos the head is a little bit too wide."
“但并不完全，因为头有点过宽了”
It was very exciting and interesting to think
这样思考非常令人兴奋和感兴趣
that there were animals of such magnitude,
有这样巨大的动物
and that they all died out
但它们都灭绝了
and at that time, nobody knew why.
并且在当时，没有人知道原因
So that's the way I was educated by my father.
这就是我父亲教育我的方式
By the age of ten, Richard had his own science laboratory at home,
十岁的时候，理查德自己已经有了一个家庭科学实验室
where he tinkered with old radios
这里他改装过旧的收音机
and experimented with physics.
试验过物理原理
He hired me, for four cents a week,
他雇用我，一周4美分
as his lab assistant,
作为他的试验助手
to amaze his friends.
让他的朋友惊奇不已
You know, there was a spark gap
你知道，那有个冒火花的间隙
with voltage against it...
有电压在上面
..and if you put your finger in,
如果你把你的手指放到中间
you get a shock.
你就会被电一下
It was my job, as part of my four cents,
这就是我的工作，作为我的4美分薪水
to put my finger in this spark gap for his friends' amusement.
把我的手指放到火花间隙为了让他的朋友吃惊
Their father, Melville Feynman,
他们的父亲，梅尔维尔·费曼
worked for a company which made uniforms.
在一家生产军服的公司工作
This exposure to the military led to a strong rejection of authority,
这种暴露在军队下的生活导致了他强烈地反对权威
a value he instilled in his son.
这是他灌输给他儿子的价值观
One of the things that my father taught me was a disrespect.
我父亲教给我的一件事情就是不要尊重权威
He'd open a picture, a New York Times, maybe it was a General,
他打开一份报纸，纽约时报，图上可能印着一个将军
and he'd say, "Now, look at these humans," he'd say.
然后他就会说“看看，现在这些人”他说
"Here's one human standing here and all these others are bowing.
“这里有一个人站着而其他人都在鞠躬”
"Now, what is the difference? Why are they all bowing to him?
“那么，这里有区别吗？为什么他们都要向他鞠躬？”
"Only because of his name and his position.
“只是因为他的名声和他的地位”
"Because of his uniform.
“因为他的军服”
"Not because of something he especially did."
“而不是因为他做了什么特别的事情”
At the age of 17, Feynman won a maths competition in New York
17岁那年，费曼赢得了在纽约的数学竞赛
and it became clear this was a subject
随后人们就知道了，在数学学科里
in which he was greatly gifted.
他具有极大的天赋
In 1935, he was awarded a place
1935，他获得了一个名额
at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, MIT.
到麻省理工学院（MIT）就读
But away from home for the first time,
但是第一次出门在外
he was going to miss more than just his family.
他想念的不光是他的家人
She was very beautiful,
她非常漂亮
Arline Greenbaum,
艾琳•格林鲍姆
the most beautiful girl on the beach.
沙滩上最美的女孩
She had great dimples and long hair down to here, when she unbraided it.
她有一对迷人的酒窝和长到腰的头发，当她解开发带时
Oh, we loved her!
哦，我们很爱她
They were not officially engaged, she was only 15.
他们还没有正式订婚，她才15岁
She was sweet.
她很甜美
We all loved her, she loved all of us.
我们都很爱她，她也很爱我们大家
From MIT, Feynman movedto Princeton,
从麻省毕业，费曼转到了普林斯顿
achieving full marks in the maths and physics entrance exam -
在数学科目和物理入学考试取得满分---
an unprecedented feat.
一个空前绝后的成绩
But back home, things weren't as perfect.
但是回到家，事情就没那么完美了
The family went away for a spring vacation
全家出发去度春假
with Arline.
带着艾琳
We went swimming
我们一起游泳
and my father saw this lump on Arline's neck
然后我的父亲看见了艾琳脖子上的肿块
and said to her, "What is that?"
然后对她说“那是什么？”
And she didn't know, but she went to a doctor
她说不知道，但她去看了医生
and it was the tuberculosis.
得知那是肺结核
We were all heartbroken.
我们都感到十分痛心
It was before there was any medicine for it.
在那之前没有任何的药物可以治疗这个疾病
And although she was sick and dying, he married her,
但是尽管她生病且生命垂危，他仍就与她结婚了
because he wanted to take care of her.
因为他想要好好照顾她
It was very hard on my mother,
这对我母亲来说很苦恼
because she was afraid he would catch tuberculosis.
因为她担心他可能也会感染肺结核
But...
但是
..my mother wasn't given a choice.
我母亲没有选择的余地
The couple braced themselves for life in the shadow of TB.
在肺结核的阴影下夫妇俩相互鼓励着对方
But another menace was about to disrupt their time together.
但是另一个威胁将要瓦解他们在一起的时间
每一个人都握有一把通往天堂之门的钥匙，
这把钥匙打开了地狱之门。
--费曼引用自佛教谚语
Just months before Richard and Arline were married,
就在理查德和艾琳结婚的一个月前
America was drawn into the Second World War,
美国被迫卷入了第二次世界大战
following the bombing of Pearl Harbor.
在珍珠港袭击事件之后
Feynman was asked if he wanted to join a top-secret project
费曼被问到是否想要加入一项绝密的计划
based in a Government laboratory at Los Alamos, in New Mexico.
地点在美国新墨西哥州 洛斯·阿拉莫斯 的政府实验室
Code-named Manhattan,
代号为曼哈顿
its objective was to build an atom bomb.
这项计划的目的就是制造原子弹
The fear was that Germany
人们担心德国
would invent such a terrifying new weapon first
率先研制出恐怖的新式武器
and use it to win the war.
然后用它们赢得战争
There was nothing that I knew that indicated
就我所知，没有任何事情表明
that if we could do it, they couldn't do it
如果我们可以做到，他们不能做到
and therefore, it was very important to try to cooperate.
因此，合作显得至关重要
Germany was the centre,
德国是中心，
the intellectual centre of theoretical physics.
理论物理学家的中心
They knew the power of this - that if Germany got this first,
他们知道原子弹的威力 如果德国率先研制成功
we have to make sure that they don't rule the world.
我们就不得不确保他们不能统治世界
I felt I should do in order to protect civilisation, if you want.
我觉得我应该为了保护文明去做，如果你这样想
Feynman became a member of the Manhattan Project at Los Alamos.
费曼成为了曼哈顿计划的一员在洛斯·阿拉莫斯
Here, he joined some of the world's finest physicists,
这里，他加入了世界上部分最优秀的物理学家的行列
pooling their combined brainpower to try to create the bomb.
联合他们群体的智慧去制造原子弹
Oppenheimer was in charge of the scientific or engineering side.
奥本海默负责系统学和工程学部分
And he was quite a heavyweight.
他也是个聪明绝顶的人
Fermi, Niels Bohr...
费米，尼尔斯·玻尔
You know, the big names of extremely high level.
你知道，这些大人物都有极其高的水平
Despite being surrounded by extraordinary physicists,
尽管杰出的物理学家都聚集在此
the challenge of developing an atom bomb so quickly
发明原子弹的挑战也来得很快
was an enormous undertaking.
那是一个艰巨的任务
One fundamental problem
一个根本的问题
was the sheer volume of calculations required.
就是需要进行的计算工作量急剧增长
Without computers, it had to be done manually,
没有电脑，这工作只好人工去做
slowing progress enormously.
很大程度上拉慢了进程
That was, until Feynman arrived.
这个问题，在费曼到来之前一直有
He found a way to get calculations going in parallel.
他发明了一个方法让运算并行实施
Still manually, still each person doing one operation at a time,
仍然是手工计算，仍然是每个人一次做一个运算
but working in parallel and then,
但却是并行工作，并且
having the parts of the calculation come back together later,
把每一部分的计算再聚到一起
so that three problems in nine months got turned around
这样把3个问题9个月解决的计划
to nine big problems done in three months.
变成9个问题在3个月之内解决
'I put on the blackboard a challenge, "Can we do it?", to the boys.
我把挑战写在黑板上，“我们能作到吗？”，对年青人说
'They all start, "Yes, we'll work double shifts, we'll work overtime,"
他们都开始行动“是的，我们将用
双班轮流制工作，我们会加班加点地工作”
'"We'll try it!"
“我们在努力！”
'As a result, we did problems nearly ten times as fast.'
‘结果，我们应对这个问题的速度比以前快了10倍’
He somehow got this team of human computers
他不知怎么的就将一个团队变成了人类电脑
to work at an inhuman pace
以非人的速度进行工作
and got things to roll.
而且能随机应变
And that was when his scientific seniors,
之后他的科学前辈们
the big shots of science at that time,
当时的科学大家们
first became aware of this fellow.
第一次注意到有这样一号人物
Despite being a key member
尽管作为一个关键人物
of the most secret Government project of the war,
在战时的最高密的政府项目中
Feynman's streak of maverick mischief was never far away.
费曼的特立独行和恶作剧从没消停
'So I used to pick the locks all the time
‘我过去常常开他们的锁
'and point out that it was very easy to do,
‘并且告诉他们开他们的锁很容易
'and every time we had a meeting of the whole...everybody together,
‘每次我们全体开会...所有人一起
'I'd get up and I'd say that we have important secrets
‘我就会站起来说我们有重要的机密
'and we shouldn't keep them in such thing. We need better locks!'
我们不能把机密保存在这样的东西里，我们需要更好的锁
Between safecracking and doing physics calculations,
开保险箱和做物理计算
the pace of life at Los Alamos was relentless.
洛斯·阿拉莫斯的生活节奏是无情的
But for Feynman, it was a welcome distraction.
但对费曼来说，却乐在其中
In a sanatorium nearby,
在附近的疗养院
his wife Arline was confined to her bed,
他的妻子艾琳卧床不起
slowly dying of her disease.
疾病一点点地侵害着她
At that time,
在当时
dry climates were believed to be good for tuberculosis.
干燥的气候被人相信有助于肺结核的好转
So although he was at high altitude,
但他在高海拔
she was at a lower altitude, in a hospital.
而她所在的医院在低海拔
I remember the day she died.
我记得她去世的那天
She was 25.
她才25
He was 27.
他才27
He was broken-hearted.
他非常地伤心
Then, in the aftermath of his grief,
然而，还没有从悲伤中走出来
Feynman was forced to confront the reality
费曼就不得不面对他参与
of what he had helped create.
制造原子弹的现实
'They gave out dark glasses that you could watch it with.
他们分发了墨镜以便你可以观看它
'20 miles away,
20英里之外
'you are not going to see a damn thing through dark glasses.
透过墨镜你将看不见那个该死的东西
'Well, I figured the only thing that could really hurt your eyes,
不过，我能肯定那东西会伤害你的眼睛
'bright light never can hurt your eyes, is ultraviolet light that does.
强光决然不会伤害你的眼睛，而是紫外线辐射伤害了你眼睛
'So I got behind a truck windshield,
所以我躲在一辆卡车的挡风玻璃后面
'so the ultraviolet can't go through glass, so that would be safe
这样紫外线辐射不能穿透玻璃，我也就能幸免于难了
'and so, I could see the damn thing.
而且，我可以看到那个该死的东西
'I'm about the only guy in the world
我可能是世界上第一个
'that actually looked at the damn thing in the first Trinity test.'
在Trinity试爆的时候真正目睹这个该死的东西的人
Three weeks later, America prepared to detonate a second atom bomb.
三周后，美国人准备引爆第二颗原子弹
This time, it wasn't a test.
这次，不是测试
He had been...
他曾经...
..expected to go as the scientist,
期待作为一个科学家
with the first flight.
参与这次飞行
But the bomb was so successful,
但这颗炸弹很成功
they decided they didn't need a scientist, so he did not go.
他们觉得他们不需要科学家 ，所以他没有去成
Otherwise, he would have been in that plane.
不然，他可能就在那架飞机上了
The bomb exploded above the Japanese city of Hiroshima,
炸弹在日本的广岛市上空爆炸
on the 6th August 1945.
时间1945年8月6日
It killed more than 80,000 people.
它致使超过80000人死亡
Three days later, a second bomb was detonated - at Nagasaki.
3天之后，第二颗原子弹被引爆---在长崎
There was a very considerable elation and excitement.
这令人感到十分高兴和振奋
And there was kind of parties and people got drunk and...
政府和人民都沉浸其中
..it would make a tremendously interesting contrast
它也造成了一个非常巨大的反差
of what was going on in Los Alamos
洛斯·阿拉莫斯正在发生的事情
at the same time as what was going on in Hiroshima.
和同时正发生在广岛的事情
Feynman was deeply disturbed by the knowledge
费曼被原子弹的知识深深困扰着
he had contributed to the deaths of so many.
他参与的工作导致如此多的死亡
He had had this great triumph on the technical level at Los Alamos,
在洛斯·阿拉莫斯，他取得了技术层面上的巨大成功
and then, of course, a terrible let down afterwards...
然后，当然，随后就是一个糟糕的失望...
..having run this tremendous race, and then, at the end of it,
...进行这场巨大的竞赛，然而，竞赛的最后，
concluding that it wasn't, in fact...
结果并不是很好，事实上...
..worthwhile.
...没什么价值
In the months after this double trauma -
在这双重创伤的一个月后-
first, losing his wife,
先是，失去了他的妻子
then, realising the destruction he'd helped unleash,
随后，他目睹了自己创造的原子弹的破坏力，
Feynman was thrown into darkness.
费曼深陷于痛苦之中
Maybe from just the bomb itself,
也许只是因为炸弹本身
and maybe for some other psychological reasons,
又可能是因为其他一些心理原因
I had just lost my wife,
我刚刚失去我的妻子
I was really in a kind of depressive condition.
我真的是处在一种十分压抑的状态
从一个新的观点认识一件旧事物是令人高兴的事情
理查德•费曼
In the autumn of 1945,
在1945年的秋天
Feynman was invited to become a professor
费曼应邀成为教授
in the Physics Department at Cornell University.
在康奈尔大学物理系
But he was still shaken by the events of the summer.
但他依旧没有从夏天的那件事中恢复过来
They expected me to be wonderful to offer me a job like this,
他们预期我能很好的胜任，于是给了我这样一个工作
and I wasn't wonderful.
但我并不能胜任
I though to myself, "I haven't done anything important.
我心想“我并没有作出什么重要成果”
"And I'm never going to do anything important."
“并且我也从来没有做出什么重要的成果”
But I used to enjoy physics and mathematical things
但我过去常常沉浸在物理和数学中
and because I used to play with it, it was never very important.
因为我过去常常把玩它们，并不觉得很重要
But I used to do things for the fun of it.
但我过去为了取乐经常与它们打交道
So I decided, I'm going to do things only for the fun of it.
所以我觉得，我与它们打交道只是为了从中获取乐取
While Feynman was rediscovering the fun in physics,
当费曼正在物理学中发现乐趣的时候
science was in crisis.
科学正处在决定性的时刻
For many years, new discoveries about how atoms behave
多年来，关于原子行为的新发现
had been throwing physics into turmoil.
使物理学一度陷入混乱
Old assumptions about the world were being proved wrong.
关于世界的旧的假设已经被证明是错的
This new problematic area of physics was christened Quantum Mechanics.
这个充满疑问的物理学的新领域叫做量子力学
Quantum Mechanics, in a lot of ways,
量子力学，从许多方面来说
was the most profound psychological shock
都给物理学家有史以来
that physicists have ever had in all of history.
从未经历过的最深刻的心理冲击
Newton was not right.
牛顿是错的
You can know everything there is to know about the world
对于这个世界，你可以知道你想知道的一切
and yet, you cannot predict with perfect accuracy
然而，你还是不能用完美的精度
what will happen next.
来预测接下来要发生的事
Quantum Mechanics had revealed the problems
量子力学提出了这样的问题
of accurately predicting how atoms
那就是如何准确预测原子
and their electromagnetic forces would behave.
和它们的电磁力的行为
And because these are the fundamental building blocks
因为它们是物质世界的基本构成模块
of nature, it threw everything else into doubt too.
它也把其他所有的事情都置于怀疑之中
Everything that happens around you, other than gravity,
你周围发生的每一件事，除了引力之外
all the immediately experienceable parts of the world,
所有能够直接体验的部分
are electromagnetism at work.
都是电磁学在起作用
When two atoms get together to form a molecule,
当两个原子聚到一起形成分子
that's electromagnetism, so all of chemistry is electromagnetism.
这就是电磁学，所以所有的化学都是电磁学
And if that means all of chemistry is electromagnetism,
而如果这意味着所有的化学都是电磁学
then, guess what?
那么，你猜怎么着？
All of biology is electromagnetism.
所有的生物学都是电磁学
Literally, everything around us is a manifestation of electromagnetism
自然的，我们周围的每一件事都是电磁学的一种显现
one way or another.
以这样或那样的方式
A new field, called Quantum Electro-Dynamics, or QED, emerged
一个新领域，被称作是量子电动力学，或简称QED，诞生了
to try to make sense of electromagnetism
去试着解释电磁学
and sub-atomic matter.
和亚原子物质
Sometimes QED seemed to work,
有些时候QED看上去很有用
but other times, its predictions were way off.
但有些时候，它的预测错的很离谱
It was all crazy, it didn't make any sense. It gave you infinity.
这完全是疯了，它没有任何意义，它给我们的结果是无穷
Infinity is not an answer. Nothing is infinity.
无穷并不是一个答案，没有什么东西是无穷的
We don't measure in the lab infinity, you get a finite answer.
我们不会在实验室测量无穷大，你得到的是一个有限的结果
You can't have your basic fundamental theory of physics
你不可能由你的基本的物理理论
give you infinity.
导出无穷
These predictions of infinity
这个无穷的预测结果
were stumping the smartest physicists on the planet.
难住了地球上最聪明的物理学家
Even the father of QED, Paul Dirac, was foxed.
即使是QED的发明人，保罗·狄拉克，也困惑不解
When I was a kid, I read Dirac's book,
当我还是个孩子的时候，我读过狄拉克的书
and he had these problems that nobody knew how to solve
他的这些问题并且没有人知道如何解决
which he described there.
正如他书中所述
I couldn't understand the book very well
我并不能很好地理解这本书
because I really wasn't up to it.
因为我还没有达到那个水平
But there, in the last paragraph at the end of the book, it said,
但在这，在这本书的最后一段，他写道
"Some new ideas are here needed."
“这里需要一些新的想法”
And so, there I was, some new ideas were needed.
因此，我在这，这里需要一些新想法
OK, so I started to think of new ideas.
好，于是我就开始思考一些新想法
Perhaps typically,
可能通常看来
Feynman's inspiration for his new ideas was unconventional.
费曼新思想的灵感来源非同寻常
When I was eating lunch,
当我在吃午饭的时候
some kid threw up a plate in the cafeteria
一些孩子在自助餐厅扔盘子
which has a blue medallion on the plate,
盘子上有蓝色的圆形图案
the Cornell sign in the cafeteria.
是康奈尔大学自助餐厅的标志
And as he threw up the plate and it came down,
当他把盘子扔出去然后盘子落下来时
it wobbled and the blue thing went around like this.
摇摇晃晃，那个蓝色的图案就像这样在动
And I wondered what the relation was between the two.
于是我就想知道这两者有什么联系
See, I was just playing.
你瞧，我只是在娱乐
No importance at all.
一点也不慎重
So I played around with the equations
于是我开始摆弄
of motion of rotating things.
旋转事物运动的方程
And I kept continuing to play with it.
我一直不断地摆弄它
And this rotation lead me to a similar problem
随后这个旋转使我想到了一个类似的问题
of the rotational of the spin of the electron
即满足狄拉克方程的
according to Dirac's equations.
电子自旋旋转的问题
And that just lead me back
这就使我重新审视起了
into quantum electro-dynamics
量子电动力学
Everything just poured out.
所有的东西一倾而出
It was just like letting a cork
这就好像把软木塞从瓶子上
out of a bottle.
拔掉一样
Inspired by the spinning plate,
受到转碟的启发
Feynman realised that the fact the equations resulted in infinity
费曼意识到这个方程导出无穷这一事实
didn't mean they were wrong.
并不意味着它们错了
The problem just needed to be looked at from a new perspective.
这个问题只是需要从一个新的观点出发来看它
It turns out that that kind of challenge was perfectly suited
事实证明,这种挑战非常合适
for someone like Richard Feynman,
像费曼这种人
who, surprisingly maybe, didn't like to speculate.
可能让你吃惊的是，这种人不喜欢推测
He wasn't the kind of modern physicist that we celebrate
他不像那种我们所赞美的现代物理学家
who's always coming up with a new theory of the multi-verse
总是提出新的关于多元宇宙的理论
or forces of nature or whatever.
或是自然界的力或者别的什么
He really liked to work in the context
他很喜欢在这种背景下工作
of things that were supposed to be understood
就是事情已经很明了了
and just understand them better than anybody else.
而他比别人知道的更清楚
To work around the infinites in QED,
在解决量子电动力学的无穷问题时
Feynman came up with a truly revolutionary idea.
费曼提出了一个真正革命性的思想
It was such a strange solution not even his sister,
这个解法如此奇怪，甚至他的妹妹
by then, a physicist herself,
那时，她也是名物理学家
recognised it as serious work.
也不觉得这是个严肃的工作
Richard said to me, "Would you go in the room and get my papers?
理查德告诉我说“能帮我到房间里把我的文件拿来吗？”
"I want to start working and my papers are in there."
“我要开始工作，我的文件都在那”
So I went in the room, and I looked...
于是我走进房间，然后我看见了...
there was no mathematics, it was these silly little diagrams,
上面没有数学公式，上面只有些无聊的小图形
and I came out and said,
我就走出来对他说
"Richard, I can't find your papers,
“理查德，我找不到你的文件”
"it's just these kind
“只有一些像这样的
"of silly diagrams."
“无聊的图形”
He says, "That is my work!"
他就说“那就是我的成果！”
The simple little diagrams Feynman had invented
费曼所发明的这个小图形
were a brilliant way to sidestep the complicated calculations
是一个绝妙的方法，用来回避量子电动力学
required for QED.
所需的复杂计算
They were a sort of shortcut,
它们是一种捷径
allowing him to avoid the infinities
让他既避免了无穷
and make meaningful predictions about the world.
又可以做出对世界有意义的预测
He saw that there was actually a sort of pictorial way
他看出实际上存在一种形象化的方法
of thinking about these pictures, these equations.
来思考这些图画，这些方程
You could associate a little cartoon,
你可以把方程中的每一项
a little Feynman diagram, as we now call them,
都与一小幅卡通相联系
to every one of these terms in the equation.
今天的人们就把它叫做费曼图
Other people would have to work for months
如果换作其他人可能要忙上好几个月
and he would get it in an afternoon.
而他得到这种方法只用了一个下午
And eventually, that's what got his ideas noticed,
渐渐的，他的图示法使他的思想引起了注意
because he's getting the right answer
因为他得到了正确答案
and he's doing it much simpler,
而他得到答案的过程更加简单
even though no-one understood what he was doing.
尽管没有一个人明白他在做什么
It turns out to be so useful that now we're applying it
事实证明这个方法很有效，现在我们把它应用于
to completely different fields that aren't particle physics at all.
完全不同的领域，一点也不涉及粒子物理学
When we look at the evolution of galaxies
当我们看着星系的演变
and large scale structure in the universe,
和宇宙中大规模的结构
we're finding that Feynman diagrams
我们发现用费曼图
are a helpful way of calculating those quantities as well.
来计算这些量也十分有效
Quantum Electrodynamics,
量子电动力学
which is the theory that Feynman put the finishing touches on,
这一理论，费曼做了一个收尾工作
is the most numerically precise physical theory ever invented.
该理论也是有史以来数值最精确的物理理论
In recognition of this work, in 1965,
1965年，这一结果被公认
Feynman was awarded a Nobel Prize for Physics.
费曼获得了诺贝尔物理学奖
He shared it with two other physicists,
他与另外两个物理学家分享了这个奖
Julian Schwinger and Sin-Itiro Tomonaga,
朱利安·施温格和朝永振一郎
who were also working on the same problem.
他们也在努力解决这个问题
Was it worth a Nobel Prize?
解决这个问题值得的诺贝尔奖吗？
I don't know.
我不知道
I don't know anything about the Nobel Prize.
诺贝尔奖的事我完全不知道
I don't understand what it's all about or what's worth what
我不明白这个奖是关于什么的，或者什么东西值得得什么奖
and if the people in the Swedish Academy decide
如果瑞典皇家科学院的人决定
that X, Y or Z wins the Nobel Prize, then so be it!
谁，谁，谁获得了诺贝尔奖，那就这样吧！
I think it was entirely right and proper.
我认为这完全是正确的和适合的
It was one of the best-earned Nobel Prizes
我会说，这是有史以来颁发的
there ever was, I would say.
最有价值的诺贝尔奖之一
I don't see that it makes any point that someone in the Swedish Academy
我不认为某个瑞典皇家科学院的人决定某项成果得奖
decides that this work is noble enough to receive a prize.
这项成果就优秀到值得得奖
I've already got the prize.
我已经得到了奖品
The prize is the pleasure of finding the thing out.
奖品就是发现这件事物的喜悦
The kick in the discovery.
在发现的时候中奖
The observation other people use it.
看着别人使用它
Those are the real things!
那些才是货真价实的！
The honours are unreal to me.
对我来说荣誉是虚的
I don't believe in honours.
我不相信荣誉
It bothers me. Honours bothers me!
它使我感到心烦，荣誉使我感到心烦！
Honours is epaulettes. Honours is uniforms.
荣誉就是肩章，荣誉就是军服
My Poppa brought me up this way. I can't stand it. It hurts me.
我的爸爸带我走上了这条路，
我受不了荣誉，它深深地伤害了我
不要试着在你的脑中填满科学，
在你的心中填满爱就足够了
理查德•费曼
In 1959, on a trip to Europe,
1959年，在前往欧洲的旅途中
Feynman met Yorkshire woman Gweneth Howarth.
费曼遇见了来自约克郡的女士格温妮丝.豪沃思
A year later, they were married.
一年后，他们便结了婚
Back in California, now Professor of Physics at Caltech,
回到加州，成为加州理工学院的物理学教授的费曼
Richard and Gweneth started a family.
和格温妮丝开始了家庭生活
I got a kick, when I was a boy, of my father telling me things,
当我还是个小孩的时候，我很喜欢父亲给我讲东西
so I tried to tell my son things that were interesting about the world.
所以我试着给我的孩子讲关于这个世界的有趣的事情
He was an excellent father.
他是个很棒的父亲
Always up to explaining things or do things.
总是在解释事物或研究某事物
We would go on walks after dinner, my father and I,
我们会在吃完晚饭后散步，我的父亲和我
and talk about things and...and it was, you know,
一起讨论一些事情...就是这样，你知道
it was wonderful and delightful.
那很棒而且很愉快
I asked him about things and he tried to explain them.
我问他什么他就努力试着解释什么
Physics and math and history and politics and science fiction
物理的，数学的，历史的，政治的，科幻小说的
and life, the universe and everything.
生命的，宇宙的，一切事情
I'm very lucky that I got to do that two or three times a week.
我很幸运，我每周有两三天的时间可以和父亲散步问他问题
Say, "Let's go for a walk." Sure!
我说“我们去散个步吧”没问题！
Growing up with Richard Feynman as your dad was never dull,
理查德·费曼做你的父亲，你的成长路上一定不会无聊
particularly if you were his teenage daughter.
特别是如果你是他的十几岁的女儿
My parents ordered a car, a van that we could all go camping in,
我的父母买了辆车，一个可以足够我们全家去露营的面包车
and they had it painted,
他们在上面画了些图案
which was so...so odd,
那种看上去很...很莫名其妙的图案
because they weren't like this at all.
因为他们平时一点也不喜欢画图案
My father may have been immune to embarrassment,
我的父亲可能已经对这种尴尬的情况已经有了免疫
but I certainly was not!
但我肯定受不了！
And they had, you know, the diagrams painted on it.
但他们却做了，你知道的，那些图还是画上去了
So most people thought they were Indian designs,
于是许多人以为那是印度的图案
but I remember once we'd just gone to McDonalds
但我记得有一次我们刚到麦当劳的时候
and we were in the parking lot and walking out to the car,
我们到停车场去正从车上走下来时
and someone asked us, "Why is your van covered in Feynman diagrams?"
有个人就问我们说“为什么你们的面包车上画满了费曼图？”
And Mother says, "Because we're the Feynmans!"
我母亲就说“因为我们就是费曼的家人”
Feynman's reputation as a communicator of science
费曼作为一个科学传播者的名声
was spreading around the world.
遍布世界各地
In the early 1960s,
在1960年代早期
he began presenting lectures for the public, which were televised.
他就开始出席公开演讲，通过电视转播
APPLAUSE
【掌声】
I'm going to discuss how we would look for a new law.
我要讨论我们如何寻找一个新的定律
In general, we look for a new law by the following process.
一般来说，我们通过下面的流程来寻找一条新定律
First, we guess it.
首先，我们靠猜
LAUGHTER
【笑声】
Don't laugh. That's really true.
别笑，就是这样的
Then we compute the consequences of the guess.
然后我们就来计算这个猜测的结果
If it disagrees with the experiment...
如果它和实验结果不一致...
..it's wrong.
..它就是错的
In that simple statement is the key to science.
这一简单的陈述就是科学的关键
It doesn't make a difference how beautiful your guess is.
它和你的猜想有多漂亮没关系
It doesn't make a difference how smart you are,
它和你有多聪明也没有关系
who made the guess, or what his name is.
不管是谁提的猜想，或他的名字有多响亮
If it disagrees with the experiment, it's wrong.
如果被实验证明它不可行，那它就是错的
That's all there is to it.
如此而已， 岂有他哉!
LAUGHTER
【笑声】
Caltech invited him to re-write the physics curriculum
加州理工学院聘请他为本科生
for undergraduates. His new course,
改写物理课程. 他的新课程
spanning the entire history of physics,
涵盖了整个物理学的历史
became known as 'The Feynman Lectures.'
被称为“费曼物理学讲义”
All these lectures had a certain amount of excitement...
所有这些课程有一定数量的令人激动的事物
and an element of what you might call
并带有一点特殊的风格，你可以
solid showbiz demonstration.
把它叫做纯娱乐式表演
I'm sure you're all familiar with the joke
我相信你们都熟悉这个笑话
about the fact that the average family in the United States
事实上全美平均每个家庭
seems to have two-and-a-half children.
大概都有两个半的小孩
It doesn't mean that there's a half a child in any family, whatever,
不管怎样，这绝不意味着任何家庭里有那半个小孩
the children come in lumps!
孩子们都被打包了！
LAUGHTER
【笑声】
He was very visual. He told jokes.
他很生动，也讲笑话
He had a unique way of explaining things
他用独到的方式解释事物
and sometimes that was a slight problem
有时那只是个小问题
because he was so engaging, you'd walk out of a lecture thinking,
因为他很有个人魅力，你会觉得那不是在演讲
"Well, that all made complete sense."
“嗯,那全都讲得通”
But, of course, five minutes later, you couldn't really remember all the connections.
但是，当然，五分钟之后，你不可能真的记住了全部的联系
You were just swept along by Feynman's personality,
你只是被费曼的个人魅力
by his humour, by his analogies.
他的幽默，他类比的事例所吸引
Graduate students started idolising him,
研究生开始把他当成偶像来崇拜
but by the 1960s his course here at Caltech was very famous.
但到了1960年,他在加州理工学院的课程已经非常出名了
Outside science, Feynman's interests were also flourishing.
在科学之外，费曼的兴趣也十分丰富
He'd become an accomplished bongo player.
他不光成为了娴熟的邦哥鼓演奏者
And he developed a love of painting and drawing,
也发展了自己对油画和素描的热爱
based on a close friendship
这是由于他和左赐恩
with renowned Californian artist, Jirayr Zorthian.
这一著名的加州艺术家是好朋友
"Jirayr", he said. "You don't know a thing about physics,
“赐恩”，他说，“你对物理一窍不通”
"and I don't know a thing about art.
“而我对艺术一窍不通”
“And yet we both admire Leonardo Da Vinci.
“但我们都很欣赏列奥纳多·达·芬奇”
“What do you say, we become two Leonardo da Vincis?
“你说啥，我们会成为两个达·芬奇？”
He said, “One Sunday I will give you a day of physics
他说“这个星期天我给你讲物理”
“and the following Sunday, you give me a day of art.
“下个星期天，你给我讲艺术”
When he started, he was absolutely an amateur.
当他刚开始的时候，他完全是个业余爱好者
Just very, very...crude.
就是非常，非常...生硬
He drew a picture of me when I was,
他画了一个我的头像，当时我还
when I was young and very fidgety,
当时我还很小很好动
and, and it just has, you know he just has my, my head,
而且，而且那画，你知道他只画了我的，我的头
some hair, and then, and then like my hands up here,
一些头发，还有，还画了一张手像这样摆着
so clearly I was kind of like, "Oh, I don't really want to do this."
所以很明显我当时的样子好像在说“哦,我真的不想这样做”
It's pure with his, um, that he can see the gesture.
画面很单纯，嗯，就是他能看到的姿势
I think he maybe got a kick out of working with his hands,
我想他可能通过动手
but particularly the pen and doing features of people.
特别是动笔并捕捉人们的特点，获得了绘画的乐趣
In the end, he became a very accomplished draftsman.
最后，他成为了一位非常娴熟的绘图者
So enthusiastic an art student was Feynman,
费曼作为一个狂热的学习绘画的学生
that he took to spending time in Giannoni's, a strip bar in Pasadena.
他甚至花时间到吉安诺尼，帕萨迪纳市的一个脱衣舞吧
Here, he divided his attention between sketching the girls
这里，他把注意力集中到画女孩的草图
and solving physics equations.
和解物理方程上
Other physicists couldn't understand it.
别的物理学家对此很费解
And say, "You know, Feynman is supposed to be a physicist
并且说“你知道，费曼本应是个物理学家的”
"and he is a brilliant, brilliant physicist
“并且是一个非常杰出的物理学家”
"and we need his input very often in Caltech.
我们需要他经常投入在加州理工学院
"We need him to talk to us about physics.
“我们需要他来给我们讲授物理”
But what does he do?
但是他究竟在干什么呢？
He goes off and spends all his time with go-go girls,
他放下了这些，把他所有的时间都花在歌舞表演女孩
bongo drummers and artists.
邦哥鼓和艺术上
He wastes so much time.
他浪费了太多时间
on people 'I don't see  what they give him.'
在那些'我不知道他们带给了费曼什么'的人身上
'But I think that Feynman got a lot out of these people
但我觉得由于费曼结识了许多这样的人
'and it enriched his life.'
才使他的生活变得多姿多彩
In the 1960s, Feynman took a sabbatical year.
在1960年，费曼得到了一次年假
But instead of heading for a different physics department
但不是去别的州的
the other side of the country, he simply crossed the Caltech campus
不同的物理系，他只是简单地在加州理工学院校园
to study an area which had long fascinated him - viruses.
转向研究另一个一直吸引着他的领域---病毒
During this time, he also became fascinated
在这期间，他也痴迷于
by the social structure of ants
蚂蚁的社会结构
and enthralled by the potential applications of nanotechnology.
被纳米技术的潜在应用深深吸引
In the long term of what he wanted to do this year and next year,
从长远来看，他对自己今年想要做什么明年想要做什么
he would think about...
会考虑一些...
figuring out some secret of the universe,
弄清一些宇宙的奥秘
but in terms of day-to-day or hour-to-hour
但在日常的工作中
he was always guided by, what seemed interesting and fun
他总是寻求，看起来有趣的，好玩的
and just sort of an intuition for the right thing to work on.
直觉上觉得正确的事情去做
In the early 1980s, his son Carl's budding career
在1980年代早期，他的儿子卡尔所在的
in the emerging field of super computers proved irresistible.
新兴的超级计算机领域这行不可抗拒地吸引了费曼
He signed up for a summer job at Carl's start-up company in Boston.
他在波士顿的卡尔的新兴企业报名参加了一个暑期工作
'We were a bunch of MIT students starting a company.'
我们这一伙开创这个公司的都是麻省理工学院的学生
So, the first day we start the company,
于是，我们开始运营公司的第一天
literally, I get this knock on the door, I open the door.
当时，我听到了这样的敲门声，于是我打开门
And he showed up and he said, "Feynman reporting for duty, what should I do?"
他就突然出现在我眼前并向我说
“费曼前来报到,我的任务是什么？”
Salutes.
紧接着一个敬礼
I think, "Uh oh, I haven't figured out what I'll do with this guy!"
我就想“啊哦，我还没想好派给这家伙啥任务！”
I mean, I've got a Nobel Prize winning great physicist...
我的意思是说，我有了一位获得
诺贝尔奖的伟大的物理学家...
So, I've had a quick meeting
所以，我就开了个简短的会议
and trying to come up with some project that was worthy of Feynman.
试着提出一些适合费曼来做的项目
So, some people said, "We want you to think about applications
于是，有人就说“我们希望你考虑下我们的并行计算
"of our parallel computing."
的应用程序”
The application of parallel processing to quantum chromodynamics.
并行应用处理器用来计算量子色动力学
He said, "No, come on, that's, that's nonsense, you know."
他说“不，别胡闹，那，那没什么意义，你知道的”
"What do you really want me to do?
“你到底想让我做什么？”
And, I said, "Well, actually, you know
于是我就说“好吧，实际上，你知道...”
"we don't really have any pencils or paper..."
“我们没有半张纸和笔...”
He said, "Right, I'll go out and buy some!"
他就说“好的，我马上就去外面买点回来！”
So, his first duty was to go out and buy the stationery for the company.
就这样，他的第一份工作就是出去给公司买文具用品
All the paper clips and pencils and so on.
所有的回形针和铅笔等等
That was his first assignment.
这是他的第一个任务
'Thinking Machines', as the company was called,
这家公司名为“思维机器”
would go on to become a major player
后来成为世界上
in the world of Parallel Super-computing,
并行超级计算机行业的重要参与者
with Feynman applying his methods of shortening calculations,
费曼用来缩短计算时间的方法
developed in the 1940s, to the new digital age.
是1940年代提出来的, 公司把它带入新的数字时代
And as always, working with Feynman
和一样以往 ，和费曼一起工作
was filled with welcome distractions.
总是充满着乐趣
We both liked spaghetti, because it was easy to cook,
我们都很喜欢意大利面条，因为它很容易煮
and I ask him why it was that when you broke a piece of spaghetti
有一次我问他，为什么你把意大利面条弄断的时候
it often broke into three pieces, instead of two?
它总是断成三节而不是两节呢？
You should try it, it really does.
你应该试试，真的是这样
So, of course, he came up with a theory of it immediately,
所以，当然的，他马上就提出了一个这样的理论
but instead of being satisfied with it
但他并不满足于这个理论
he constructed an experiment to see if the theory was true,
他还设计了一个实验来看看这个理论是否正确
which involved slowly moving the spaghetti off the end of the table
实验内容包括将意大利面条慢慢移向桌子边缘
and breaking it at different lengths.
然后以不同的长度让它折断
And then, that theory was wrong and he came up with another theory
结果，这个理论被否定，他就提出了另一个理论
and then each theory would lead to another experiment.
然后每个理论都会导出一个新的实验
By the time the evening was over, we had broken spaghetti
到了大晚上，我们已经把弄断的意大利面条
all over the place and we STILL didn't know why
搞的到处都是，但我们依然不知道
spaghetti broke in three places.
为什么意大利面条会断成三段
This playful curiosity coupled with the anti-authoritarian values,
这种顽皮的好奇心加上被他父亲灌输的
instilled by his father, frequently led Feynman down a mischievous path.
反独裁的价值观，让费曼看上去总是很淘气
He's just so funny and irreverent.
他就是这么的滑稽和玩世不恭
You have to kind of look at that picture a few minutes and think...
你得看看那张照片几分钟然后想着...
"Oh my gosh, he's really, you know!
“哦我的天哪,他是真的,你知道！”
"Making nice little horns!"
“他在别人头上用手比了一个小角”
Important people. You know. "Oh yes, I think now would be a great time."
很重要的人士，你知道“嗯，是的，我觉得现在很值得留恋”
He didn't need the external validation
他不需要外在的证明
of having everybody respecting him all the time,
他一直受每一个人的尊敬
because he respected himself, he knew he was an extraordinary person.
因为他尊重自己，他知道自己是个特殊的人
And if he came off as kind of a doofus
如果他在一些他不认识的家伙面前
to some guy that he doesn't know, it's OK.
表现得像一个笨蛋，这种感觉不错
Because he knows inside that he's a man of substance.
因为他心里知道自己是个人物
In 1984, Feynman collaborated with his friend, Ralph Leighton
1984年，费曼与他的朋友拉夫·莱顿合作
on a humorous book of anecdotes from his life.
用一本幽默书来记录他一生的趣闻轶事
'I opened the safes which contained all the secrets to the atomic bomb.'
‘我打开了包含所有原子弹的秘密的保险柜’
It was kind of accidental how the books caught on.
这本书的流行完全是个意外
The publisher released the first one,
出版商在1985年1月
Surely You're Joking, Mr Feynman, in January of 1985.
发布了第一期《别闹了,费曼先生》
And the edition was like 2,000 copies or some low number.
这一版只印了大概2000册或者更少
And in January.
而且在一月份
I was thinking, January, the whole holiday season is over,
我就想，一月份，整个假期都已经结束了
who's going to buy a book in January?
谁还会在一月份买书啊？
But people did buy it.
但人们还真就买了
And Surely You're Joking, Mr Feynman quickly became a best seller.
于是《别闹了,费曼先生》立刻就变成了畅销书
It remains to this day,
时至今日
one of the biggest-selling science books of all time.
它一直都是最畅销科普书之一
I do remember coming down one evening and seeing him
我清楚的记得一天晚上我下楼来正看他
just, you know, giggling
在，你知道，咯咯地笑
and clearly enjoying the book that he was reading.
显然,他很享受这本他正在读的本书
And I sort of looked, you know, "What are you reading?"
于是我就有点想看看，你知道，“你在读什么？”
And he held up the book so I could see that it was his own,
于是他举起书，我就看到了，那是写他自己的书
Surely You're Joking. And he said, "Ah, such a character."
《别闹了,费曼先生》，他就说“啊，很有个性啊”
Freely admitting that, yes, he was laughing at his own history.
直率地承认了自己，是的，他在嘲笑着自己的历史
The book vividly captured Feynman's world view,
这本书生动地描绘了费曼的世界观
the sense of curiosity and fun guiding him through life.
好奇感和好玩感引导着他的一生
It was an approach he communicated to an even bigger audience through
世界各地更多的观众通过一系列的BBC纪录片，广播
a series of BBC documentaries, broadcast around the world.
来更好的走进费曼
I have a friend who's an artist and he's sometimes taken a view,
我有位艺术家朋友，他有时采取这样一种观点
which I don't agree with very well.
一个我并不赞同的观点
You hold up a flower and say, "Look how beautiful it is." And I'll agree.
你拿起一朵花然后说“看它多漂亮”这我同意
And he says, I, as an artist, can see how beautiful this is,
然后他说，我是个艺术家，可以看懂这花的美丽
but you, as a scientist,
但是你，作为一个科学家
take this all apart and it becomes a dull thing.
把它研究透了，它也就变得索然无味了
And I think that he's kind of nutty.
我认为他的想法有点怪
First of all, the beauty that he sees is available to other people
首先，他看到的美对其他人而言都是等价的
and to me too.
对我也一样
I believe, although I may not be quite as refined aesthetically
我相信，尽管我没有像他那样
as he is, that I can appreciate the beauty of the flower.
有十分雅致的审美，但我依然可以赞美那朵花的美丽
At the same time, I see much more about the flower than he sees.
同时，关于这朵花，我看到的比他更多
I could imagine the cells in there, the complicated actions inside,
我可以想象它的细胞，它里面的复杂反应
which also have a beauty.
那同样很美
I mean, it's not just beauty at this dimension of one centimetre,
我的意思是说，它的美丽不光表现在这种程度上
there's also beauty at a smaller dimensions, the inner structure.
在更微观的世界里它也同样美丽，它的内部结构
Also the processes.
它的反应过程也是
The fact that the colours and the flower are evolved in order to
事实上花的颜色和它的逐渐进化是为了
attract insects to pollinate it is interesting.
使昆虫更青睐于给它授粉
It means that insects can see the colour.
这就意味着昆虫可以看见花的颜色
It adds a question,
这也萌生了一个问题
does this aesthetic sense also exist in the lower forms?
这种美感也存在于低等生物里吗？
Why is it aesthetic?
它为什么会审美？
All kinds of interesting questions, which a science knowledge only adds
一朵带有香气的和神秘感的令人着迷的花
to the excitement and mystery and the aura of a flower.
科学知识只是将各种有趣的问题附加给它
It only adds. I don't understand how it subtracts.
它只是附加，我不知道如何减去
Most people only have a few stories.
大多数人只有几个故事
You and I might have three or four stories to tell.
你或者我，可能有那么三两个故事可说
Some people have ten, and Feynman had hundreds.
有的人可能有十个，而费曼有数百个
And Feynman was so mesmerizing.
而且费曼极具魅力
I think Chris Sykes in his documentaries,
我认为克里斯.赛克斯在他的纪录片中
captured Feynman how he was.
很好的抓住了费曼的形象
He takes enormous pleasure in finding out about things
片中的一切都表现出费曼在发现事物
and exploring life and everything it has to offer.
和探索生命时所获得的巨大的快乐
More than that, he takes tremendous pleasure in telling you about it.
不仅如此，他在告诉你的时候更是显示出极大的快感
I think he was pleased with how it worked out,
我认为他对解决问题感到很满足
that he was able to communicate with so many people,
并且他能与许多人交流
sort of his view of the world and of nature and so on.
分享自己对世界对大自然的看法等等
When I was a student at Caltech, I went up to Feynman's door
当我还是加州理工学院的学生时，我走到费曼的门口
and knocked on it and a door opened and I explained
然后敲门，门开了，我解释说
that my mother had watched his programme about him,
我妈妈看了他的有关他自己的节目
thought he was interesting, she had no science background,
认为他很有趣，她没有科学背景
and I said, "Do you think you could write to her
我说，“你看你能不能给她写封信
"because maybe I'll have a better chance of teaching her physics?"
“因为这样我可能就有机会教她物理学？”
And Feynman did write to her. He wrote a letter in which he said,
然后费曼就真给她写了封信. 在信中他说
"Dear Mrs Chown. Ignore your son's attempts to teach you physics.
“亲爱的乔恩女士.  不要理睬你儿子想教你物理的尝试.
"Physics is not the most important thing. Love is."
“物理不是最重要的事情. 爱才是最重要的”
So it kind of backfired.
就这样，真是事与愿违啊.
I got the greatest living physicist at the time
我遇到了那时候最伟大的活着的物理学家
telling my mother that physics isn't important.
他却告诉我妈妈说物理学不重要
That love was the important thing.
爱才是重要的事情
Through his films and books, Feynman had touched the lives of millions.
通过他的电影和书籍，费曼影响了许多人的生活
Yet there was something all this success
但有些事情不会因为
and recognition couldn't alter.
成功和认知而改变
I did a lot of running and Feynman thought,
我经常跑步，然后费曼就想
gee, that's a healthy thing to do, so he started running too.
嘿，这事有益身心健康啊，于是他也开始跑步
And when you start running regularly, you lose weight.
而且当跑步成为你的生活的一部分时，你就可以减肥了
And Feynman suddenly noticed that one side kind of bulged out.
然后费曼忽然感觉腹部的一侧有什么东西凸出来了
They discovered a big mass in his abdomen.
他们就发现在他的腹腔下有一个大肿块
He came home and reported,
他回到家告诉我们说
"It's the size of a football. It's consumed one whole kidney."
“它有橄榄球那么大，几乎耗损了一整个肾脏”
And he says, "Well, I went to the medical library
他接着说“没事，我去过医学图书馆”
"and I looked things up and I figure
“我知道这东西而且我断定”
"it's about a 30% chance it'll kill me."
“这东西只有30%的可能要了我的命”
So, you know, not the kind of thing you want to hear from your father.
所以，你知道，你不会想从你父亲那听到这样的事
But exactly the kind of thing he would say.
但他却告诉了我们这一事实
And...
然后...
He sort of quit working at that point, because, you know,
他辞掉了当时的工作，因为，你知道
surgery and chemotherapy and so on, it's a full time job.
手术和化疗等等，得没日没夜的做
One day his secretary Helen Tuck called me up
有一天他的秘书海伦·塔克给我打电话
to tell me that Dick had cancer and that he was going to the hospital
告诉我迪克得了癌症，下个星期五
for an operation the following Friday.
要去医院做手术
It was a very dangerous operation
那是个非常危险的手术
and it was not assured that he would survive it.
而且这个手术不一定能保证他活下来
I promised not to tell anyone and he didn't know that I knew.
我保证不告诉其他人，而且他
并不知道我了解到的有关他的情况
And I told him that somebody had found an apparent error
于是我就告诉他在我们合作发表的计算中
in a calculation that we had done and published together.
有人发现了其中存在一个明显的错误
And so on Monday morning we met in my office
于是，在星期一的早上，我们在我的办公室碰头
and he sat down and started working, and he was consumed by it.
然后他就坐下来开始解题，随即便沉浸于此
All his energy and attention was devoted to solving this problem.
他所有的精力和注意力都放在求解这个问题上了
And we worked on it all day long.
就这样，我们一起忙了一整天
And finally at six o'clock in the evening,
最后在晚上七点钟的时候
we decided the problem was intractable, it couldn't be solved,
我们觉得这个问题很棘手，解不出来
we couldn't figure out what the answer was.
我们没办法算出答案是什么
And we gave up and went home.
于是我们就都放弃回家去了
Two hours later, he called me at home to say he'd solved the problem.
两个小时后，他在家就打电话给我，
告诉我说他解决了那个问题
He hadn't been able to give up, and stop working on it
他不可能放弃，也不可能罢手
and finally he'd found the solution.
最终他找到了解决方案
He dictated the solution to me over the phone, told me what it was,
他把答案通过电话口述给我，
告诉我答案是什么
and he was exhilarated, absolutely walking on air.
并且十分兴奋，完全都飘飘然了
Feynman would recover from this first operation for cancer.
费曼从第一次癌症手术中恢复了过来
But the disease would never completely go away,
但这一疾病再也不会从他身上完全消失
and he would always be living under its shadow.
他将一直要活在病魔的阴影下
对于一个成功的技术
现实必须置于比公共关系优先的地位，
因为大自然是不会被愚弄的
理查德•费曼
'We have main engine start. Four, three, two, one. And lift off.
“我们的主引擎已经启动，四，三，二，一，发射了”
'Lift off of the 25th space shuttle mission
第二十五次航天飞行任务起航
'and it has cleared the tower.'
它照亮了发射塔
'Challenger go with roll programme.'
挑战者号开始转身指令
'Roger. Roll, Challenger.
‘罗杰，转动，挑战者号
'Good roll, programme.'
‘转的不错
In January 1986, NASA launched its 25th space shuttle mission.
1986年1月，美国宇航局(NASA)启动第25次航天飞行任务
It symbolized a new era of space flight by adding a school teacher
它象征着一个太空飞行的新纪元，因为一个中学老师
called Christa McAuliffe to the crew.
克丽斯塔•麦考利夫也加入了队伍
'65 final. Thank you.'
‘第65条执行完毕，谢谢’
'Challenger. Go with throttle up.'
‘我是挑战者.现在节流控制上调
I was in social studies and I think we were taking a test and
我正在上社会课程，我记得我们当时正在考试
the teacher came in and said, "We've had a horrible accident."
老师就走进来说“我们遇到了一个可怕的事故”
'Flight controllers here looking very carefully at the situation.
“飞行控制器在这里密切关注形势”
'We have no down link.'
‘我们没有下行线路’
And then coming home, and my parents had already seen it,
然后回到家，我的父母已经看了全过程
which was unusual because they didn't really watch TV.
这太不寻常了，因为平时他们不会
一本正经地坐在电视机前
'Watch your data carefully.'
‘仔细看看你的资料’
'Take hard copies of all of your displays.
把你所有的显示复印下来
'Make sure you protect any data source you have.'
‘确保你所保护的任何数据源’
The loss of their space shuttle and its crew of seven, live on TV,
电视直播了他们失去的航天飞机和7名宇航员
shocked America. The country was thrown into mourning.
此事震惊了美国，全国陷入哀痛之中
Our nation's loss is first a profound personal loss
国家的损失首先是我们宇航员个人
to the family and the friends and the loved ones
的家庭，朋友，爱人
of our shuttle astronauts.
的彻底损失
But there was one question everyone wanted an answer to -
但有一个问题所有人都想知道答案--
what had gone wrong?
到底是什么出了问题？
A Presidential Commission was hastily put together to find out,
总统委员会马上被召集起来以查明原因
but it was comprised largely of space industry insiders
但这个委员会是由大量的与NASA
with close ties to NASA.
关系密切的业内人士担任的
Someone independent with unimpeachable scientific credentials was needed.
委员会还需要有声望的利益不相关的科学界人士
I have a policy practically of never going near Washington.
我有一个行事原则，从来不接近首都华盛顿
And I called up various friends of mine
我打电话给我的各种朋友
who were connected to the space programme one way or the other
他们或多或少都与这项太空计划有关
and tried to ask them if they didn't see
我就试着去问他们是否考虑过
whether I should go or somebody else could do it just as well.
我是不是也应该参与调查或者别的人也可以来调查
His friends were, "Dick, you got to go
他的朋友就说“迪克，你应该去”
"cos you're the only guy who can cut through the bullshit!"
“因为你是唯一可以揭穿谎言的人”
He asked me what I thought he should do
他问我，我认为他该做什么
so I just asked him, "Do you think it's an important problem?"
于是我就问他“你觉得这是个很重要的问题吗？”
And he said, yes he did.
他说,是的
I said, "Do you think you can make a difference?"
我说“你觉得你责无旁贷吗？”
And he said, after a while, he said, "Well, yeah, probably can."
过了一会，他说“嗯,是啊,也许可以”
I didn't say another word.
我就再没说什么了
And after a few minutes hesitation he said, "To hell with you, Hibbs,"
犹豫了几分钟之后，他说“见鬼去吧，希布斯”
and hung up.
然后就挂了
Feynman broke his policy and within days of the accident
费曼打破了自己的原则，事故之后的几天
he had joined the inquiry in Washington.
他也加入了在华盛顿的调查
The investigation was led by William Rogers,
调查的负责人是威廉·罗杰斯
an ex-Secretary of State and the ultimate Washington insider.
前国务卿和华盛顿消息灵通人士
His formal, bureaucratic approach was
他那一套正式的，官僚主义的方式
the polar opposite of the freewheeling maverick professor.
与随心所欲，特立独行的教授截然相反
Mr Rogers, he knew nothing about it.
但罗杰斯先生并不知道这一点
I had been on accident boards before and I took the opportunity.
之前我登上过失事飞船，于是我抓住机会
I said "Hey, I just did one of these investigations,
我说“嘿,我刚好做过一项调查,”
"would you like to see it?"
“你想看看吗?”
And I think reluctantly Rogers said
我觉得当时罗杰斯很不情愿地说
"Yeah, OK, you can show it to us,
“嗯，行，你可以拿给我们看看”
"but we're not going to do it that way."
“但是我们不会这样做”
And so I went through this very logical step-by-step process of
因此我就审查了这份非常逻辑化的规范流程
of how you investigate a space accident and Rogers said,
这份流程适用于调查太空事故，而罗杰斯说
"No, we don't have the technical capability to do that."
“不，我们没有这个技术能力按这种方式做”
And that's when Feynman butted in.
这个时候费曼插了一杠子
He said, "No, I like that. I think that's a smart way to go."
他说“不，我觉得很好，我觉得那是个聪明的方法”
For Feynman and the chairman,
对费曼和主席来说
it was the beginning of a poor relationship,
这是他们不好关系的开始
but for the professor and the Air Force General,
但是对教授和空军上将 来说
it was the start of a close friendship.
这是他们好关系的开始
And he just was the smartest guy in the world.
他是这个世界上最聪明的人
And he had a reputation for integrity, you know,
而且他也有着为人正直的好名声，你知道
he was the most honest guy in the world.
他是这个世界上最诚实的人
He didn't accept something unless he really could prove it.
他从不接受任何事情，除非他真的可以证明它
The two men began touring the US,
这两人开始游历全美
visiting NASA sites where the shuttle was made,
拜访了制造太空飞船的NASA的协助单位
questioning the engineers and managers.
询问了工程师和管理者们
In the process of speaking to the engineers, he realised,
在和工程师们对话的过程中，他注意到
"Wow, some of them won't talk to me right now cos
“哦,他们中的一些人现在不愿和我说话”
"the managers are in the room," you know?
“因为那些管理者在房间里”你知道吗？
It wasn't simply a technical puzzle,
这并不是一个简单的技术问题
there was a human puzzle going on too.
这里面也掺杂了人为迷局
Writing home to Michelle and Gweneth,
在写给家里的米歇尔和格文内斯的信中
Feynman expressed his frustration and excitement
费曼对他猎取到的真相
at his hunt for the truth.
表达了他的失望和兴奋
'Dearest Gweneth and Michelle.
‘亲爱的米歇尔和格文内斯’
'This is the first time I have had time to write to you.
‘这是我第一次有时间给你们写信’
'I already smell certain rats that I will not forget because I just
‘我已经确实已经像猫一样闻到了
老鼠的味道，绝对不会忘记，因为
'love the smell of rats, for it is the spore of exciting adventure.'
‘我很爱这个味道，那是令人激动的冒险的开始’
But there was a problem, NASA managers didn't want to reveal
但当下有一个问题，NASA的经理不愿透露
the full extent of their knowledge.
他们全部的信息
The result was a smokescreen.
那个结论是个障眼法
NASA wanted to control everything that they gave
NASA想要控制对委员会提供的一切
to the Commission and actually withheld things.
并隐瞒真实的情况
They didn't lie,
他们不是撒谎
but they certainly didn't go around blabbing the truth either.
但他们也不会真的到处去泄露真相
What Feynman didn't know was that
费曼所不知道的是
General Kutyna had a secret source inside NASA.
库缇娜上将在美国宇航局有一个秘密的消息源
Sally Ride was America's first woman in space
萨莉·莱德是登陆太空的第一位女性
and another Commission member.
也是另一个委员会成员
She privately told the general that NASA had long had doubts
她私下里告诉上将NASA一直怀疑
about how the rubber O-rings,
用于航天飞机固体火箭助推器的
the seals in the shuttle's solid rocket boosters,
O型塑胶垫圈
worked in the cold.
在寒冷气候下的工作状况
The temperature on the morning of the launch had been below freezing.
发射的那天早晨，发射站的温度达到了冰点以下
The general needed to get this information to Feynman
上将需要把这一信息告诉费曼
without compromising his source.
又不损害他的消息来源
The chance came after supper one evening at Kutyna's house.
机会终于在一天晚饭后的库缇娜的房子里等到了
The general restored classic cars.
上将修理他的老爷车
I took him out in the garage to show him the car
我把他带到车库向他展示那辆老爷车
and Feynman really isn't interested in cars.
但费曼真的对车不怎么感兴趣
So we walked around the car and I showed him the interior
于是我们就绕过车子，接着我就向他展示了内部结构
and I showed him where the engine was.
我告诉他哪是引擎
And Feynman looked at my work bench
这时费曼看到了我的工作台
and he sees a couple of carburettors out there.
他看到一对汽化器摆在那
And he says, "Kutyna, what are those carburettors?"
他就说“库缇娜，那些是汽化器吗？”
And I said, "Oh, they're from the Opal and I keep one put together
我说“哦，它们产自澳宝，我把放在了一起的”
"and then one I take apart and clean."
“其中一个拿起来拆开清理了一下”
And then the thought came to me.
这时一个想法出现在我脑海中
I needed to get the idea of cold and O-rings and leakage across.
我要把寒冷、O型环和泄漏的想法提出来
I said, "You know, Professor, these doggone carburettors have O-rings
我说“你知道吗，教授，这些该死的汽化器的O型环”
"and they leak when they're cold."
“总是因为寒冷的原因而泄漏”
Feynman had his answer and he also had an inspired idea
费曼有了答案，同时他也有了一个启发性的想法
about how to convey it to the world's press.
来把这个答案告知公众媒体
From that and the various things that you told me
从那件事情和各种事情，你告诉我
about the need for resilience and the lack of resilience...
关于弹性的需求和弹性的缺乏
When the Commission next met, he began questioning
当和委员会第二次会晤时，他开始质问
senior engineers about the effect of cold on the O-rings
高级工程师关于发射那天早上
on the morning of the launch.
寒冷气候对O型环的影响
Their replies were evasive,
他们的回应就是托词
denying that temperature could have had an effect.
否认温度会对它造成影响
Before the event, from information that was available
在出事之前，从我们所知的信息
and the understanding that was available,
和我们已经明白的事实
was it fully appreciated everywhere that this seal
难道还不能重视在某个温度下
would become unsatisfactory at some temperature?
任何一处的垫圈会变的不安全吗？
And was there some sort of a suggestion of a temperature at which
还有一些关于温度的问题是否
the SR...the SRB I guess you call it...
在RS...RSB(助推器)上，我想你们这样称呼它...
Yes, that's right...Shouldn't be run?
是的，是这样叫的...是不适合的？
It was the judgment that under the conditions that we would see
这一判断只是基于我们所看到的
on launch day, given the configuration that we ran,
发射那天，我们运行的装配
that the seal would function at that temperature.
这种垫圈在这种温度下依然有效
That was the final judgment.
这就是最终的结果
It was Feynman's chance.
这是费曼的机会
He decided to use the power of a classic science demonstration.
他决定利用经典的科学演示实验的力量
During the hearings, they had that actual O-ring joint
在听证会期间，在他们谈到关于O型环接点的时候
and were passing it up the rows.
对方避而不谈
It goes to Feynman.
轮到费曼时
I'm sitting to his left and I hand it to him and he puts it down.
我坐在他的左手边把东西递给他，他把东西放在桌上
And then he goes into his pocket and pulls out the pliers and the
之后他把手伸进自己的荷包掏出一把钳子，
hose clamp and the screwdriver, and takes the joint apart.
软管夹和螺丝刀，把接点拆开
Pulls out the piece of rubber O-ring, puts the clamp on it,
抽出一段O型橡胶环，把它夹在螺丝钳上
then I know what he's going to do.
然后我就知道了他准备干嘛了
He sees the ice water and he swears it was just kind of an accident.
他看着冰水，并发誓说那是偶尔想到的
He got this idea, "Wait a minute, I know I know how
他有了这个想法“等一下，我知道，知道是怎么回事”
"I can get data on how rubber is when it's cold."
“我可以得到当橡胶变冷时的数据”
He clamped a piece of rubber and put it in a beaker full of ice water.
他夹住一段橡胶然后把它放在装着冰水的烧杯里
I took this stuff that I got out of your seal and I put it in ice water.
我把这个取自你们密封舱的垫圈放进冰水里
And I discovered that when you put some pressure on it for a while
随后我就发现当你对它施加压力保持一会儿
and then undo it, it maintains, it doesn't stretch back,
再释放压力，它保持变形状态，没有再反弹回去
it stays the same dimension.
一直保持着这个尺寸
In other words, for a few seconds at least,
换句话说，至少几秒钟，
and more seconds than that, there's no resilience in this
或者比这个时间多几秒，这种特殊的材料
particular material when it's at a temperature of 32 degrees.
在32度时就没有弹性了
I believe that has some significance for our problem.
我相信这对我们的问题至关重要
The O-rings, which were supposed to create a seal
那个O型环本应该是密封在
around the solid boosters, had got so cold they'd lost their ability
固体助推器的密封舱内，当它变得很冷的时候
to flex and to fill the gap between the boosters.
它就失去了弹性和填补助推器之间的空隙的能力了
And that's why the fuel had leaked and the shuttle had exploded.
这就是为什么燃料会泄露和航天飞机会爆炸
Feynman had nailed, once and for all,
费曼这一举，板上钉钉
that the cold could have been the cause
证实了在发射的73秒后
of the shuttle's failure just 73 seconds after launch.
因为寒冷而导致航天飞机的失事
It really was a turning point in the investigation.
这次调查是一个真正的转折点
It couldn't be ignored.
它决然不能被忽视
In the summer of 1986, the Commission's report was submitted.
1986年的夏天，该委员会的报告被提交了上去
In its appendix, Feynman added a stark reminder
在报告的附录中，费曼加了一个严肃的
about the limits of science.
关于科学的局限性的提醒
His last recommendation I think
他最后的建议，我认为
really summed it up in one simple paragraph.
是真正的一小段总结
"For a successful technology,
对于一个成功的技术
"reality must take precedence over public relations,
现实必须置于比公共关系优先的地位
"for nature cannot be fooled."
因为大自然是不会被愚弄的
I remember, it was very hard on him.
我还记得，癌症对他的负担有多大
He was just exhausted. He came over, he says,
他非常的疲惫，他来拜访我时，他说
"I came over to tell you that my cancer's come back again.
我来是来告诉你我的癌症又复发了
"Doesn't look too good."
看起来并不乐观
So I don't know what we talked about and I don't know how
但我忘记了我们谈论的内容，并且也忘了
I got off on the subject.
我是怎么转到这个话题的
I said, "I've been thinking about an invariant in turbulent flow."
我说“ 我在思考在一个紊流中的不变量”
He said, "What do you mean?"
他问“你是什么意思？”
I explained a little bit what it was all about.
我稍微解释了一下那究竟是怎么回事
The invariant, you know.
那个不变量，你知道的
I said, "Well under these, such and such conditions."
我说“在这些，那些和那样的条件下”
And he says, "Let's see."
他说“让我们看看”
So I had a notebook there.
于是我就拿出了一个笔记本
He took the notebook and he started, he wrote it all down step by step.
他拿着笔记本就开始算，他把步骤一步一步地写下来
I think it took 13 steps to get to that.
我记得他写到13步的时候得到了结果
He says, "Yes, that's true, it is an invariant."
他说“是的，那是真的，它确实是个不变量”
Then he says, "You got me thinking about physics again.
然后他说“你让我又重回了一遍物理的思考”
"I can go home now."
“我现在可以回家了”
Feynman went into hospital for the last time in February 1988.
在1988的二月，费曼在医院度过了他的最后时光
His kidneys were failing and he decided
他的肾脏不行了并且他决定
he didn't want to go through with dialysis to prolong his suffering.
他不打算通过透析来延长自己的痛苦
I still sort of thought, "No, this isn't the way it is."
我仍稍稍想过“不，事情不应该是这样的”
But he was able to handle a lot of physical difficulties
但只要他的头脑清醒依然可以解决
as long as his mind was sharp.
很多的物理难题
When a person is dying, their hands move a little.
当一个人临终前，他们的手会这样动
And the nurse who was there says that he's not
当时在那里的护士说他并不是
trying to communicate,that's just natural.
试着要交流，那种举动很正常
And he raised his hands like this.
然后他就把手像这样举起来
And he went like this, which, if you know it, is the symbol that
然后他就想这样做，这个，如果你知道，那是
a magician gives when he's going to do a trick. OK?
魔术师当他们准备变东西的时候所做的动作，好吗？
And he went...
然后他就这样做...
He was communicating, again, of his observations of the world.
他再一次通过这种方式交流了对世界的看法
The doctors were wrong, he could hear.
医生错了，他听得见
He could move if he tried hard enough.
如果他尽力还是可以动的
And understand... He could hear and understand what was being said.
也可以理解...他可以听到和理解正在说的事
And those were his last words.
这就是他最后的遗言
Richard Feynman died on the 15th February 1988
理查德·费曼于1988年2月15日
in hospital in Los Angeles at the age of just 69.
在洛杉矶的医院去世，年仅69岁
When I took my last walk with Richard Feynman, he was telling me
当我最后一次和理查德·费曼散步时，他告诉了我
a bunch of funny stories, but I realised the message behind
许多有趣的故事，但我意识到，这些故事背后的信息就是
the stories was that he was about to die of cancer and I got very sad.
费曼将死于癌症，这让我很伤心
And he noticed it and he asked me, "What's wrong?"
而他察觉到了这点，就问我“怎么了？”
And I said, "I'm sad because I'm realising that you're about to die."
我就说“我伤心是因为我觉得你将不久于人世”
And he said, "Yeah, that bugs me sometimes too.
他说“是啊，这个问题有时我也头疼”
"But not as much as you'd think," he said, "because you realise
“但并不是你想的那样”他说“因为你意识到了”
"that at some point in your life, you've told a lot of stories
“在你生命中的某个时刻，你讲了很多故事”
"and those stories are going to stay around even after you're gone."
“并且这些故事在你离去之后仍会继续流传”
Today, over 25 years since his death,
今天，他离开我们已经有25年多了
Feynman's prophecy has more truth than he could ever have imagined.
费曼的预言已经成为现实，而且现实已经超过了他的设想
Through an invention that hadn't been created when he died,
通过一项发明，费曼的故事依然流传
his stories do live on.
这项发明在费曼去世时还没有呢
Because through their reimagining on the World Wide Web,
因为通过在互联网上的重加工
a new generation is discovering the delights of time with Feynman.
新一代的人们发现了费曼的快乐时光
It's fantastic to just be able to Google Feynman, Richard Feynman,
你只要在谷歌中输入费曼，或理查德·费曼
you know, any kind of variation and there it is.
任何类似的词语，就能找到有关的东西，真是太奇妙了
You have a lot of stuff out there.
你在那里可以找到许多费曼的材料
I see my father referenced in popular culture a lot more now
我看到我父亲在许多现在的大众文化中被引用，
than when he was alive.
次数比他活着的时候还多
I have a friend who's an artist and he's sometimes taken a view,
我有位艺术家朋友，他有时采取这样一种观点
which I don't agree with very well.
一个我并不赞同的观点
You hold up a flower and say, "Look how beautiful it is." And I'll agree.
你拿起一朵花然后说“看它多漂亮”这我同意
And he says, I, as an artist, can see how beautiful this is,
然后他说，我是个艺术家，可以看懂这花的美丽
but you, as a scientist, take this all apart and it becomes a dull thing
但是你，作为一个科学家，
把它研究透了，它也就变得索然无味了
and I think that he's kind of nutty.
我认为他的想法有点怪
You wonder what Feynman would have made of the internet.
你一定想知道互联网上的费曼会是个什么样子
And I think he would really, really like the idea
我认为他真的,真的会很喜欢这个主意
that he's spread all over the world in clips, short and long,
通过或长或短的剪辑将他传播到世界各地
on the internet, for maybe all time. I think he'd like that.
的因特网上，也许每时每刻都在传，我认为他会喜欢的
You know, you just touch it like this...
你知道的，你只要像这样触碰一下它...
FEYNMAN'S VOICE
【费曼的声音】
..and you bring his voice right back, you know.
...你马上就把他的声音带了回来，你知道的
'"The whole universe is in a glass of wine."
“整个宇宙都在一杯酒中”
'I don't think we'll ever know in what sense he meant that.
“我不觉得我们会知道在何种意义上他要这样比喻”
LAUGHTER
【笑声】
'For the poets don't like to be understood.'
‘因为诗人不喜欢被理解’
I know what I'll remember him for.
我知道我会记得他
For being a good brother and a good person.
作为一个好兄弟和一个好人
He wasn't just the scientist, he wasn't just the artist,
他不光是一个科学家，也不光是一个艺术家
he wasn't just the educator.
也不光是一个教育家
He was physics with a human face, you know.
他本人就是人性化的物理学
He showed that in order to be a top-ranked physicist
他证明了要成为一个顶级的物理学家
you can still be a human being.
你不用不食人间烟火
I think that's a very important legacy to people
我认为对于那些想从事科学研究的人来说
who want to do science.
这是费曼留给他们的一项重要遗产
It's a human endeavour and he showed that.
这项遗产就是一个人的努力，是他展示给我们
Has Richard Feynman inspired you to follow your own path in life?
理查德•费曼曾经鼓舞你去走自己的人生之路吗？
Join The Open University to explore your options and find out more
加入开放大学探索你的选择和了解更多
about how he revolutionised the face of physics.
关于他如何彻底变革了物理学的故事
Go to:
请访问：
And follow the links to The Open University.
以及到开放大学的链接
天马字幕组 中文字幕
原创翻译：马天一   校对：旧语新思
http://growupsoft.blog.163.com
请勿用于商业用途，转载请保留译者信息
Subtitles by Red Bee Media Ltd